# 四伯爷以前你买酱油不是得买的瓶瓶儿吧？（瓶装酱油）
Uncle, did you use to buy bottled soy sauce in the past?
# 以前哪里有瓶装的呢
There was no bottled soy sauce in the past
# 都是打的散装酱油吧
So it was all sold in bulk?
# 一个大坛子装 装满在哪里
Before, it was contained and sold in a big vat
# 然后拿竹子筒筒儿
And people used bamboo tubes
# 称一斤一斤一斤家的竹筒筒儿装一斤
Bamboo tubes as measuring containers
# 用竹筒筒儿提起来就是一斤
One bamboo tube of soy sauce was 1 jin (500g)
# 倒在瓶子里
And then pour it into a bottle
# 就是一个厂厂儿【漏斗】
via a funnel
# 所以说以前叫做打酱油
So that's why it's called "to fetch soy sauce"
# 后面对卫生要求这块比较严格了
Eventually there were stricter requirements on public health
# 所以说后来把它做成包装的
So it became a pre-packaged product
# 后来就是包装的卖的包装货
Yeah, eventually it was sold in packages, pre-packaged products
# 但是以前酱油会生蛆你晓得不
Do you know that in the past maggots could grow in soy sauce?
# 要安
Yeah
# 生蛆其实是正常的
It's actually normal to have maggots
# 是盐蛆都嘛
Yeah, those are "salt maggots"
# 以前打煤油用的那个打烧酒还不是用的那个啊【漏斗】
In the past, we used that (funnel) for fetching kerosene. And also for fetching baijiu (liquor)
# 竹筒筒锯个口子
We used a bamboo tube, with a notch cut on it
# 等一下吃了饭我跟你普及一下酱油的知识吧
After we eat, let me share some soy sauce knowledge with you
# 就是说瓶装酱油的知识
Basically, bottled soy sauce knowledge
# 瓶装酱油的知识你那里又是怎么样瓶装的嘛又
Knowledge of bottled soy sauce... What's that?
# 就是那一些品牌的那些酱油啊
Basically the branded bottled soy sauce types
# 就是教你以后卖酱油看那些地方
I'll teach you what to look for when buying soy sauce in the future
# 教你认识什么是好酱油
and how to recognize what is a good soy sauce
# 啥子是崴【假】的啥子是正宗【真】的
Which ones are fake and which are authentic?
# 嗯对啥子是崴的啥子是正宗真的
Yeah, which are fake and which are real
# 也不是说崴假就是他的等级不一样
Actually, they are not fake. Just of different grades
# 分等级
Oh, they are graded
# 等级不一样
Different grades
# 跟我卖肉一样有槽头肉有宝赖肉
Same as me selling pork. Like "caotou", "baolai" (different cuts)
# 有三线肉有腿子肉有货架肉
"sanxian", "tuizi" and "huojia"
# 是
Yep
# 还有尾巴肉这些就是这样分的
And also tail cut. That's how it's divided
# 我懂起了
Ah, I understand now
# 以前酱油多少钱一斤呢
In the past, how much did soy sauce cost per jin?
# 以前以前八分钱一斤
8 cents for one jin (500g)
# 八分
8 cents?
# 最起头八分一角涨到一角二
It was 8 cents. Then it rose to 10 cents, and then 12
# 你知不知道现在的酱油最贵的多少钱一斤
Do you know how much the most expensive soy sauce costs these days?
# 不知道
Dunno
# 现在的酱油最贵的可以四五十块一斤
Now the most expensive soy sauce can cost 40 to 50 yuan for one jin
# 诶 有
Ai, ok
# 四五十哟
That's 40 to 50
# 是吧有
Yeah? Ok
# 我听到说过
I've heard of that
# 只不过我没有打来吃过
But I've never tried it
# 操不起【吃不起】那种高档的东西
Can't afford that kind of luxury
# 一个农村人撬则耳根卖的那里操【吃】得起那种酱油嘛
How could a peasant who lives hand to mouth afford that kind of soy sauce?
# 就是那种八九块十来块的就够了
The 10 yuan ones work just fine
# 我正好今天就买了几十块一斤的
I happened to have bought one of the expensive ones today!
# 等下就给你尝一尝
You can try it later
# 等一下你拿给我品尝一下看嘛
Let me have a taste later!
# 看是啥子滋味嘛
See how it tastes
# 要得
Sure
# 好嘛 好嘛
Yeah, yeah
# 这【纸箱】是打湿了的
The box is wet
# 等下不要把它全部掉才去哟
Got to get rid of it completely later
# 十瓶酱油
10 bottles of soy sauce
# 伯娘过来坐嘛
Take a seat here, aunt
# 这样子要办大生（生日）吗
Are you hosting a birthday party?
# 呵呵办大生【生日】
Hehe, birthday party
# 这里有十瓶
10 bottles here
# 什么牌子的都有点
We've got all sorts of brands here
# 就是一样都有点
Got one for every type
# 你猜这里面那一瓶最贵
Guess which one is the most expensive?
# 这瓶还有点好
This one looks pretty good
# 这瓶吗
This one?
# 这瓶不是最贵的
This isn't the most expensive one
# 不是最贵吗
Not this one?
# 四伯爷你猜得出来不
Can you guess, uncle?
# 这瓶
This one
# 你怎么知道是这瓶
How did you know?
# 看那个包装这些还弄得很漂亮
This one... The packaging looks pretty fancy
# 包装吗
The packaging?
# 这瓶酱油四十块钱
This bottle costs 40 yuan
# 四十块吗
40 yuan?
# 这是酱油是不是
Is this soy sauce?
# 酱油就是这瓶酱油是最贵的一瓶四十块钱
This is the most expensive one. 40 yuan for a bottle
# 其他的有十多的
Others are at about ten yuan
# 有几块钱的
or just a few yuan
# 这瓶就相因【便宜】吧这瓶
This one looks cheap
# 嗯其实我们这个酱油贵与不贵其实它这里面是有一些门道的
Actually, there is some technical knowledge determining the price of soy sauce
# 我拿个简单的给你看吧四伯爷你看
Let me explain a simpler detail (easier to understand), uncle
# 一般这个酱油都是酱造出来的酱油
Commonly, soy sauce is made from a brewing process
# 然后只要你看它好不好是看它那个氨基酸
And then, to check its quality, basically you need to check its amino acid level
# 含量越多这个就越好
The more, the better
# 然后看它那个质量等级
Also check its quality grade
# 等级越高这个就越好
The higher grade, the better
# 最高等级是特级
The highest grade is premium grade
# 还有就是看下面配料那里
Also check the ingredients
(Actually showing a nutrition facts label)
# 蛋白质也是含越多越好
The more protein, the better
# 碳与化合物这些都不是很重要
Carbohydrates are not important
# 还有就是看这个钠
Also check the sodium level
# 这个钠越高就越咸
A higher sodium level means it's more salty
# 咸的酱油肯定就没有那么好吃
If the soy sauce is too salty, it doesn't taste as good
# 还有最重要的就是这里
And here is the most important thing
# 这个叫什么你看
See what it says?
# 看不清楚
I can't see clearly
# 这个这四个字
These four characters
# 谷氨酸钠
Monosodium glutamate
# 谷氨酸钠就是味精
"Monosodium glutamate" is MSG (aka Accent)
# 很多人说我们不能吃味精不能吃味精
Many people claim that "we shouldn't eat MSG"
# 其实我们酱油里面大部分是有味精的这个
Actually, most types of soy sauce contain MSG
# 一般来说
Generally speaking...
# 这个盐在这个酱油里面得含量最好不要超过百分之六十
The salt concentration in soy sauce should not exceed 60%
# 如果一旦超过了的话这个酱油除了咸你就尝不到这个鲜味
If it exceeds 60%, then you will only taste the "saltiness" and not the "savoriness (umami)" of the soy sauce
# 它这个除了加谷氨酸钠之外还加了糖份的
Besides MSG, this one has also added sugar
# 其实这个就是酿造的时间不够 它酿造的时间不够的话他就会
If the brewing period was not long enough, they may
# 加味精
add MSG
# 加焦糖色
and add caramelized sugar
# 来调这个颜色调这个鲜味
to make up the color and the umami taste
# 其实这个就已经等级算比较低的了
Actually, because of this, it's probably a low grade one
# 他也标了这个上面等级是三级
They've labeled it as such, the label says it's "grade 3"
# 你说这瓶贵它这个贵在哪里呢
This one is expensive. Do you know why?
# 贵在它那个配料上只有水只有那个有机黄豆有机小麦加食用盐
It's expensive because the ingredients are exclusively water, organic soy beans, organic wheat, and salt.
# 它就没有加色素就是焦糖就
It has no added coloring, like caramelized sugar
# 没有加那个味精
And it has no added MSG
# 谁会去看你那个酱油好撇呢
Who cares if the soy sauce is good or not?
# 反正吃着口感好他就认为好这个酱油
As long as it tastes good, it's good soy sauce
# 但是这个酱油的话大家吃这个酱油的味道都是很多都是尝味道
Many people choose soy sauce by tasting it
# 但是这个味道
However...
# 有的人 这个很鲜
Some people may taste it and say "oh it's very umami"
# 其实你们不懂它里面加了很多味精
Actually, you didn't know there's a lot of added MSG
# 就不是特别好
which is not very good
# 现在让我们把这个酱油好的跟一般的倒在这个里面
Now we'll pour into bowls some of the good versus the average soy sauce
# 跟大家分享一下怎么去挑选这些酱油
and share with you how to choose soy sauce
# 拿这瓶来试
I'll test this one
# 你看起泡子是不是
Look, it's foaming right?
# 首先我们这个酱油把它摇这样子用力摇
First, let's shake this bottle of soy sauce. Shake it hard
# 摇了之后它会起那个很细的泡
After shaking, it forms very fine foam
# 它这个泡你放得越久它消得越慢
Then if the foam stays longer, that is, it takes a longer time to decay
# 就说明这个酱油越好
then it means the soy sauce is better
# 这只是一个检查它好不好的一个很基本的一个手法
This is just a very basic trick to check the quality
# 就是看
which is by visual inspection
# 然后就是看它那个配料那里
And then check the ingredients table
# 配料表上面一般的酱油它的产品名称这个地方会写
Normally, the product label should have
# 酱香酱油或者是什么味型的酱油
the flavor type, for example "jiangxiang" ("sauce-flavored") or some other type
# 后面一定会有一个酿造型酱油
which should be followed by "brewed soy sauce"
# 四伯爷你知不知道什么是酿造酱油
Uncle, do you know what "brewed soy sauce" means?
# 不知道
Dunno
# 就是以前那个缸缸儿【瓦岗】头
That is, in the past, we have those vats
# 就是酿的那种
the ones for brewing
# 那种就是酿的
That is brewed soy sauce
# 现在我把它弄点来倒出来
Now I'm going to pour some out
# 其实都还好就是说
Actually, these are all OK, but...
# 你们之前不是买的那种酱油很咸吗
Last time you bought a soy sauce that was very salty
# 它就是加了那个味精的吗
So it has added MSG?
# 不是加味精盐巴重得很 是加盐
Not MSG. It just has a lot of salt, they added salt
# 就是这个酱油倒在里面比其他的都咸 (this line is not subtitled in the video, 視頻沒打字幕)
That soy sauce was more salty than any other one
# 还有一种酱油就是甜的吗
Isn't there a type of soy sauce that's sweet?
# 这个酱油这个颜色怎么滴了
What's up with the color of this soy sauce?
# 这么淡呢
The color is so light
# 它淡是正常的啊
Being light is normal
# 这个是没有酿得那么久的
It went through a shorter brewing period
# 我尝一下
Let my taste it
# 四伯爷你拿筷子来试一下
Uncle, you can taste it with a chopstick
# 味道还是可以
Tastes not bad
# 味道还是可以嘎 嗯
- Tastes not bad?
- Yeah
# 我尝一下
Let me try
# 加了糖的这个
Is there added sugar?
# 少数
A little bit
# 那里嘛人家咸的那种还不是这个样子
No. Even those salty types taste like this
# 哎呀加了糖的这个
There must be added sugar
# 味道还是可以
The taste is fine
# 这个加了谷氨酸钠的加了白砂糖的配料上都写着有
According to the ingredients, this has additional MSG and sugar
# 加了盐巴的
Also salt
# 你如果吃的淡都话就吃这个
Use this one if you prefer mildness
# 这个比较淡
This one is relatively mild
# 这里都能看得到23%的盐
It says 23% salt concentration
# 所以就没有那么咸
So it's not that salty
# 这个就适合拿来拌面条那些
So it's suitable for noodles
# 吃面要得
Good for noodles
# 吃面可以蘸肉那些都可以
Good for noodles. Also good as a meat dipping sauce
# 我来拆这个40块钱一瓶的
Let me open this 40-yuan bottle
# 这瓶开给你看
Let me open it for you
# 这个就是40的
This is the 40-yuan bottle
# 40块钱
40 yuan
# 你尝一下这个味道
Have a taste
# 40块钱1瓶的味道肯定要好点
A 40-yuan bottle must taste even better
# 一点点 一点点就好 不要太多
A little, just a little. Not that much
# 这个你看它颜色都要浓点
Look, the color is darker
# 颜色浓点是因为酿造的时间更久一点
It has a darker color because of the longer brewing period
# 你看这个粘得更久 是不是
This one sticks to the bowl for longer, right?
# 这个更容易粘
This one sticks tighter
# 来尝一下它的味道
Have a taste of it
# 这个没有加味精没有加糖的
This one doesn't have added MSG or sugar
# 嗯 没加味精
Hmm, no added MSG
# 吃没吃出来 这个没加味精
Right? This has no added MSG
# 但是这个没有加味精的话
This one doesn't have any added MSG, so the flavor is...
# 就很明显
Quite obvious
# 很明显就是这个虽然说贵一点
Quite obvious. I mean, although it's kind of expensive
# 它这个酱油有一点点带涩味
there's a little bit of bitterness
# 就是说明没有加糖
which means there's no added sugar
# 没有加味精
and no added MSG
# 然后盐的话也是
And regarding salt content, it's also...
# 盐分不高
The salt concentration is not high
# 看一下
Let me check
# 盐分52%算正常
52% salt concentration, which is normal
# 蛋白质1.6%
1.6% protein
# 这个要浓一点那个要淡一点
This one looks darker. The other one is lighter
# 嗯 这个要贵一些
Hmm, this is more expensive
# 这个的酱香要重一点
This one has a stronger "jiangxiang" ("sauce flavor")
# 四伯爷这些酱油都尝了你喜欢哪一种嘛
Now we've tasted these types of soy sauce, which one do you like, uncle?
# 这个是没有加味精没有加糖的
This is the one without added MSG or sugar
# 没有加色素的
without food coloring either
# 这个就加了糖加了味精
This is the one with added sugar and MSG
# 实际上这个
Actually...
# 在我们农村来说吃起还比较可以
For rural people like us, this one tastes fine
# 顺口点
Tastes more natural
# 好啦 本期视频我们酱油就聊到这里
All right, that's all of the soy sauce conversation in this video
# 我们就拜拜
So let's... Bye bye
# 拜拜
Bye bye